The following content is
provided under a Creative
Commons license.
Your support will help
MIT OpenCourseWare
continue to offer high quality
educational resources for free.
To make a donation or
view additional materials
from hundreds of MIT courses,
visit MIT OpenCourseWare
at ocw.mit.edu.
DENIS GOROKHOV: So I
work at Morgan Stanley.
I run corporate treasury
strategies at Morgan Stanley.
So corporate treasury
is the business unit
that is responsible for
issuing and risk management
of Morgan Stanley debt.
I also run desk strategies own
the New York inflation desk.
That's the business which is
a part of the global interest
rate business, which is
responsible for trading
derivatives linked to inflation.
And today, I'm going to
talk about the HJM model.
So HJM model-- the abbreviation
stands for Heath-Jarrow-Morton,
these three individuals who
discovered this framework
in the beginning of 1990s.
And this is a very
general framework
for pricing derivatives to
interest rates and to credit.
So on Wall Street, big banks
make a substantial amount
of money by trading all
kinds of exotic products,
exotic derivatives.
And big banks like
Morgan Stanley,
like Goldman, JP Morgan--
trades thousands and thousands
of different types of
exotic derivatives.
So a typical problem
which the business faces
is that new types of
derivatives arrive all the time.
So you need to be able
to respond quickly
to the demand from the clients.
And you need to be
able not just to tell
the price of derivative.
You need to be able also to
risk manage this derivative.
Because let's say if
you sold an option,
you've got some
premium, if something
goes not in your favor,
you need to pay in the end.
So you need to be able to hedge.
And you can think
about the HJM model,
like this kind of
framework, as something
which is similar to theoretical
physics in a way, right?
So you get beautiful models--
it's like a solvable model.
For example, let's
say the hydrogen atom
in quantum mechanics.
So it's relatively
straightforward to solve it,
right?
So we have an equation,
which can be exactly solved.
And we can find energy
levels and understand this
fairly quickly.
But if you start going into more
complex problems-- for example,
you add one more
electron and you
have a helium atom-- it's
already much more complicated.
And then if you have complicated
atoms or even molecules,
it's unclear what to do.
So people came up
with approximate kind
of methods, which allow
nevertheless solve everything
very accurately numerically.
And HJM is a similar framework.
So you can-- it allows
to price all kinds
of [INAUDIBLE] derivatives.
And so it's very general.
It's very flexible to
incorporate new payoffs,
all kinds of correlation between
products and so on, so forth.
And this HJM model--
[INAUDIBLE] natural [INAUDIBLE]
more general framework like
Monte Carlo simulation.
And before actually
going into details
of pricing exotic interest
rates and credit derivatives,
let me just first explain
how this framework appears
in the most common type
of derivatives, basically
equity-linked product.
So like a very, very
simple example, right?
So let's say if we have a
derivatives desk at some firm,
and they sell all
kinds of products.
Of course, ideally,
let's say there's
a client who wants to
buy something from you.
Of course, the easiest approach
would be to find the client
and do an opposite transaction
with him, so that you're market
neutral, at least in theory.
So if you don't
take into account
counterparties and so on.
However, it's rather
difficult in general,
so the portfolios
are very complicated.
And there's always
some residual risk.
So this is the cause
of dynamic hedging.
So for this example,
very simple example,
a dealer just sold a
call option on a stock.
And if you do this,
then in principle,
the amount of money which
you can lose is unlimited.
So you need to be able
to hedge dynamically
by trading underlying,
for example, in this case.
So just a brief
illustration of the stock
markets, you see how random it
has been for the last 20 years
or so.
So first of all, this
year, some kind of--
from beginnings of the
1990s to around 2000,
we see really very
sharp increase.
And then we have dot-com
bubble, and then we
have the bank
[INAUDIBLE] of 2008.
And if you trade derivatives
whose payoff depends,
for example, on
the FTSE 100 index,
you should be very careful.
All right?
Because market can drop,
and you need to be hedged.
So you need to be able to come
with some kind of good models
which can recalibrate
to the markets
and which can truly risk
manage your position.
So the so the general idea
of pricing derivatives
is that one starts from
some stochastic process.
So in this example here, it's
probably like the simplest
possible-- nevertheless a
very instructive-- model,
which is essentially like
these [INAUDIBLE] Black-Scholes
formalism, which is where we
have the stock, which follows
the log-normal dynamics.
I have a question.
Do you have a pointer
somewhere, or not?
It's just easier-- OK, OK.
PROFESSOR: Let's see.
There's also a pen here,
where you can use this.
DENIS GOROKHOV: Oh, I see.
PROFESSOR: Have you
used this before?
You press the color here
that you want to use, say,
and then you can draw.
You press on the screen.
DENIS GOROKHOV: Oh, I see.
Excellent.
That's even better.
OK, so it seems like the
market is very random.
We need to be able to come up
with some kind of dynamics.
And it turns out that
the log-normal dynamics
is a very reasonable
first approximation
for the actual dynamics.
So in this example, we have
stochastic differential
equation for the stock price.
And it consists-- it's
the sum of two terms.
This is a drift, it's some
kind of deterministic part
of the stock price dynamics.
And here, also,
we have diffusion.
So here, dB is the Brownian
motion driving the stock,
and S is the price
of the stock here.
Mu is the drift.
And sigma is the
volatility of the stock.
Particularly, it
shows the randomness.
And it's the randomness
impact on the stock price.
And using this model, one
can derive the Black-Scholes
formula.
And the Black-Scholes
formula shows
how to price derivatives
whose payoff depends
on the price of the stock.
So here, if you look at
this differential equation,
then you can answer
the question.
Let's say if you started
from some initial value
for the stock at time t.
And then we started the clock.
Which are now to be
at time capital T.
And given that time T,
then stock price is S_T.
So what's the
probability distribution
for the stock at time T?
So this kind of equation
can be very easily solved.
And one can obtain analytically
the probability distribution
function at any
[INAUDIBLE] moment of time.
So I mean, I just think
I'll write a few equations,
because it's very important
to understand this.
So I'm sure you probably
have seen something like this
already, but let me just
show you the main ideas
beyond this formula.
So if you have a
random process--
let's say A is some process,
stochastic process, which
is normal.
So it follows some drift.
Plus some volatility term.
Right?
So the difference
between this equation
is that I don't multiply
by A here and A here.
Especially, it's much
simpler to solve.
So the solution
for this equation
is very straightforward.
So at any moment of time T,
if you start at moment 0,
the solution of the equation
would be something like this.
Drift-- right?
I'm simply integrating.
Plus-- and I assume that B of
t is standard Brownian motion,
so at time 0, it's 0.
And then it's very
easy to see now that...
is equal to the Brownian motion.
But this is nothing else.
It's some random number,
which is normally distributed,
times square root of time.
So epsilon is
proportional to it.
OK, so basically, this
means that this is normally
distributed.
And its-- and probability
distribution for this quantity
is equal to-- we know
it's exactly, right,
because this is like a
standard Gaussian distribution.
And if you simply
substitute A into here,
then you will obtain the
probability distribution
for the actual quantity.
And I'll just write it
for the completeness.
So basically, we obtain
probability distribution
for the standard variable.
So this is straightforward.
So the only difference between
the case I'm doing here
is that the dynamics is
assumed to be log-normal.
Right?
And the interpretation
is very simple.
If it's normal, then
the price of the stock
can become negative.
Which is just a
financial nonsense.
So the [INAUDIBLE]
log-normal dynamics basically
is a good first approximation.
And in this case, what
helps as a result is just
known as Ito's lemma.
So I just first of all
write it, and then I
will explain how
you can obtain it.
And if you look
at this equation--
let me write it once again--
which is basically the drift
plus-- then it turns out
that, of course, since--- it--
intuitively it's clear that the
dynamics of logarithm of S is--
dynamic of logarithm
of S is normal.
So essentially, we obtain
something like this.
So if you now substitute
this into this,
you locked in a
very simple formula.
OK, so here, I used
the result, which
is known as Ito's lemma, which
I'm going to explain right now.
Like how it was
obtained-- basically,
it tells us that when we
differentiate the function
of a stochastic variable.
Then besides the trivial
term, which is basically
the first derivative
times dS, there's
an additional term,
which is proportional
to the second derivative.
And it's non-stochastic, so
I'll explain why it's this.
But if you do it-- if you
look at this equation,
then you see essentially
this formula.
It's very, very similar
to this formula.
The only difference now is that
alpha is just mu minus one half
of sigma squared.
So that's a how, if you
iteratively use this solution,
and simply substitute
A by log S,
you will come to this equation.
So this is very important.
So it's a very important
effect, like-- yes?
AUDIENCE: The fact that
it can't be negative,
does that exclude
certain possibilities?
When there's a normal Gaussian,
can go negative or positive?
DENIS GOROKHOV: Yes, but stock--
from a financial point of view,
stock cannot be a liability.
Right?
You buy a stock.
This means basically,
you pay some money.
And you have basically
some sort of, say, option
on the profit of the company.
So they can't charge
you by default.
So it can't go
negative for the stock.
Also, in principle,
there might be
derivatives, which can be both
positive or negative payoff,
but not the stock.
So it's fundamental
financial restriction.
So very important thing.
So if you talk about the stock
dynamics and Black-Scholes
formalism, it's very
important that the probability
distribution for the stock
can be found exactly.
And I'll just
[INAUDIBLE] very briefly
go, again, through the
Black-Scholes formalism,
it's very important
just for understanding.
And I believe there are a couple
of things which, at least when
I was studying this, it
was not very clear to me,
so I want to go to
some more detail.
So basically, here,
this derivation
is almost like every textbook.
So the idea is that there
is a very fundamental result
in stochastic calculus.
That if you have a
stochastic function, function
of stochastic variable
S and time, then
its differential can be
written as the following form.
So this is all
very clear, right?
This is standard calculus?
It's straightforward.
But there is an additional term
that looks a bit suspicious.
And I will explain
what it actually
means on the next slide.
So a very important thing is
that when you calculate dC,
then you will obtain
deterministic term which
is proportional to
the second derivative.
And you see, there is no-- the
fact is that you have here dt,
basically this looks like it's
an additional contribution
to the drift.
We view this as drift,
and this is a drift.
And there is no, any
more, stochasticity.
It's very important.
This is like a crucial fact
beyond the Black-Scholes
formalism and the Monte
Carlo method in finance.
And then, the idea, you
can read, for example,
in Hull's book,
its standard proof.
So if we issue an option,
then we hedge it--
by having a certain
position in the underlying.
So the idea is like this.
Let's say I sold a call
option of the stock.
So when the stock market
goes, up I make some money.
And then, in the same
time, I short the stock,
so I lose money on my hedge.
And wherever the market goes,
I don't make or lose money.
So that's the idea,
basically, beyond hedging.
And basically, what
happens if I calculate
the change in my
portfolio, then since there
is no risk involved, I
assume I am perfectly hedged.
Then I simply obtain
the risk-free return.
So r here is the
risk-free interest rate.
So if you simply
look at this equation
and substitute the
Ito's lemma result here,
then you obtain like a
very simple equation,
which is basically
Black-Scholes differential
equation for the stock--
for the price of the option.
So this equation is
very fundamental.
And it's very elegant.
So you can see although
originally, right,
if you started from something
with some arbitrary risk,
with some arbitrary drift mu.
Right?
Which is basically--
it could be anything.
Which is that this drift mu
drops out of the equation.
And it depends on
the interest rate.
And this is a very
interesting fact.
So and this very interesting
fact has to do with hedging.
Again, you have
position in an option,
and you have an opposite
position in underlying.
And that's how the
drift disappears.
If you look at the movement
of both the positions,
then you see that there that
the drift will disappear.
So it's a very important
and striking fact.
And the second thing,
which is truly a miracle,
is that risk is
eliminated completely.
So this equation has
absolutely no stochasticity.
So you can just solve it.
If you specify
the option payoff,
and if you know your
volatility, which
is a measure of your-- basically
often how the stock fluctuates.
And if you know the
risk-free interest rate,
you can just price the options.
And this is a true
miracle that occurs.
And when I was studying
this, I couldn't really
understand this--
maybe because I
was coming from
theoretical physics,
and all this result called
Ito's lemma is buried somewhere
in stochastic calculus.
And I would just try to
understand in [INAUDIBLE] what
it all means.
And let them just
explain here, basically
how one can understand
this result, Ito's lemma,
in a very simple term.
[INAUDIBLE] terms.
So let me just write--
let me remind you.
So Ito's lemma basically tells
the following-- once again,
so if C is the function
of stochastic variables,
of stochastic variable
S, then its differential
is not just equal to some
standard result from calculus.
But we also get some kind
of very exotic term, which
is basically very nontrivial.
And let me just try to explain
to you how actually it appears.
So just to understand
this, I recommend everybody
after this lecture,
look at this derivation,
because it really explains
what this Ito's lemma means.
So the idea is very simple.
So let's start from electrons
for the first principles.
And let's say we have
an interval of time,
with length dt.
And let's say we divide
it into n intervals,
and each interval
length is dt prime.
Right?
And I assume that the
ratio of dt over dt prime
is sufficiently large.
So first, we know that
our stock, as we know,
follows the log-normal dynamics.
So this means that if I go from
from time i to time i plus 1,
here you need to
exchange i and i minus 1.
So then, you can always
[INAUDIBLE] the following form,
right?
So S at time i plus
1 minus S at time i
is equal to the
drift term-- right?
Which is a discrete version
of the stochastic differential
equation.
Plus the randomness.
So here again,
sigma is volatility.
It's the measure of how
the stock fluctuates,
which is the stock price,
which is square root of dt,
because Brownian
motion fluctuation is
proportional to the time.
And also here, we have
epsilon, and epsilon
is a standard normal variable.
Then-- OK, so we have this.
This is pretty straightforward.
Basically, I just throw
stochastic differential
equation on the latest.
And I go from point
i to point i plus 1.
Now, let's see what it means
for the price of the option.
So again, so C is the
price of the option.
At time T, when the stock
price is equal to S_(i+1).
So the change in
the option price
is equal to-- like
the first term, just
something very standard,
standard calculus.
Plus the first derivatives and
the difference in the stock
price, plus I take
the second-order term,
this is the second
derivative, and I
have here S times i plus
1, minus S times i squared.
So this is approximate, because
I'm taking only the main terms.
Or the other terms, given that
both times dt and dt prime
are very small, they
can be neglected.
So you can check it carefully
at home if you want to.
But I guarantee that
there is no miracle here.
Everything we need is here.
Now let's do the following.
So we have this equation.
And let's look at this term.
So this term, basically, is the
cornerstone of the Ito's lemma.
So let's take this
equation for the difference
and substitute into here.
And you see here, again, you
can look-- what is important,
against the time scales.
So dt prime is very small.
Therefore, the term, which
is random, dominates here.
Right?
Because [INAUDIBLE]
square root of dt.
And square root for small
times is much bigger
than the linear function.
Therefore, we simply neglect
this term compared this term.
And with linear
accuracy in dt prime,
we can approximate
this just by this term.
Now, what to do-- so again,
we wrote the same equation,
that latest difference
for the option price
of two neighboring points.
And what I'm doing right now,
I have all this equation,
and I will simply sum them--
basically from 0 to N.
So let's say I have all these
equations from 0 to N minus 1,
and I sum them.
And again, it's
very straightforward
and obtains the full equation.
And again, what is very
interesting is that we will
obtain-- you look at this term.
So this term is
very complicated.
It's essentially
stochastic right?
Because-- it looks
like very stochastic.
And because--
remember that this is
the standard normal variable.
And all of them are independent.
So in principle, we
have the sum of N
independent normal
variables squared.
And it turns out-- it's really
a very beautiful result,
and I recommend everybody
also do it at home,
I try to show you right
now on the blackboard--
that if you sum up all
this epsilon squared,
that in the limit when
N goes to infinity,
this term becomes deterministic.
So let me just
show you basically
what exactly is meant.
So what I mean by deterministic
is that of course,
if I have epsilon squared,
then it's-- there is some
probability distribution, right?
It's distributed between
0 and infinity, right?
So this is some
kind of function.
But my claim is
that once I start
adding more and more numbers--
and so on, and so on-- then
this function will become
more and more and more narrow.
So it behaves like a
deterministic random--
like a completely deterministic
variable in the large N limit.
And to do this, let me
just write a very simple--
write explicitly of what I mean.
So essentially, remember that
we have the sum of variables.
Right?
And for us to show that
it's become deterministic,
we need to show
that it squared--
The width of the distribution,
which I defined as-- let's say
you have a variable, right?
And if I defined the dispersion
in the following way,
now I define here the dispersion
for this random variable which
is equal to the sum
of epsilon squared.
So if I write it here,
then it turns out
that each term in
this equation is
proportional to N
squared, which is natural.
But it turns out that the
difference in the large N limit
is proportional only
to N. Therefore,
if you have this variable,
which-- if you sum up
more and more terms, then
we'll have a variable.
We have a distribution
for this variable, which
is moving in this direction.
And of course it
moves this direction,
but it becomes more and more
and more narrow, basically.
So as the limit of
N tends to infinity,
it becomes a deterministic.
So I'd recommend
everybody at home just do
this very simple exercise.
And you will see that
essentially, the sum behaves
as a deterministic quantity.
So just to do this,
you need to you
need to know the very
simple properties
of the standard
normal distribution.
First of all, the average
expected value of epsilon
is equal to 1, right?
For a standard normal variable.
And also, you need to know
that the fourth moment
of the normal variable
is equal to 3.
So if you have this, then
you can calculate this,
which is trivial to calculate.
And then you can come to this
property that, once again,
probability distribution
function, in the large N limit,
behaves deterministic.
It essentially becomes
like a delta function.
So this is a very
interesting result,
because it basically explains
why in the Black-Scholes
equation, we have this very
weird by deterministic term.
And that's why the option
pricing is possible.
Because if you started
pricing options--
like if you don't know
anything about Black-Scholes,
it might be that there's
no price for the option,
because it might be that
although you do hedge,
you still cannot eliminate
your randomness completely.
Maybe hedge helps you with just
too narrow the distribution
of your outcome, but we're
just not guaranteed at all.
So it's really very-- Ito's
Lemma, which is usually
in every book on
derivatives, probably
like the first
equation ever written,
basically is given
without any proof.
But this-- in reality, it's
a very interesting limit.
So it can be realized only if
you have two different time
scales.
So the small time
scale, which is dt prime
is-- in the business
sense, it corresponds
to your hedging frequency.
It's when you rebalance
your hedging portfolio.
And the time dt, there's
a time scale dt, which
is much bigger than dt prime.
It's at the time at which
you look at your portfolio.
So only in this very weird
limit, when dt over dt prime
goes to infinity, you
strictly have Ito's Lemma.
So actually, if you look
even like is most famous book
on derivatives.
If you look at this edition,
you will see actually
that the proof
actually isn't correct.
So just look at it and
find what's wrong there.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE] normal?
DENIS GOROKHOV: Sorry?
AUDIENCE: That's what it is?
DENIS GOROKHOV: Yeah, this
is what [INAUDIBLE] means.
So if you use these
two results here,
you will see that your
it's proportional only
to N, not to N squared.
So that's why your distribution
becomes more and more narrow.
Because when you sum
up, what it means
is you sum up more
and more variables.
Each of them was like
random normal variables.
So the average--
average goes like N.
But the dispersion--
the dispersion, right?
That's the standard
deviation, right?
You have a square
root of N. That's
why basically, square
root of N over N is small.
So by increasing
N, basically you
become more and more
and more deterministic.
So that's the main fact
beyond Ito's lemma.
So that's it's obtained.
So I recommend everybody just
look in detail, because this
is the cornerstone of
derivatives pricing theory,
but at many books it's
not really well-written.
So when I was studying,
it was like I couldn't
understand for a while.
So it took me a time
just to understand.
What else?
And a very interesting
thing now is
that remember that
we used Ito's lemma--
and basically, we are able
to obtain this equation.
And this equation is very
well known in literature.
It's very similar to
the heat equation.
And heat equation can be
solved using standard methods.
And I don't want to write
any derivation here,
it's relatively straightforward.
Maybe a bit cumbersome
but straightforward.
And if payoff of your
option at maturity
is given by some function, which
is not really important here.
Because you can write a
very general solution.
So what is here is
essentially Green's function
of this equation.
And this Green's function,
if you look at this equation,
is very similar to the
probability distribution
function, which we have on this
slide in the very beginning.
So this function is
identical to this function,
and the only difference
is that the drift of stock
in the real world disappears.
And we are left only
with the interest rate.
And so this equation, which
is again, also very important
for the derivatives
pricing, is how
we come up with the whole idea
of Monte Carlo simulation.
So this is nothing else as
a Green's function, which
basically tells us
how the stock evolves
in the risk-neutral space.
Risk-neutral space is
essentially some kind
of imaginary world,
like [INAUDIBLE] world,
where all the assets' drift is
just the interest rate and not
the actual drift.
So it's very fundamental.
So it's very important things
that the drift in real world
drops out of all the equations.
So the only parameter which
actually does matter for option
pricing is volatility.
So this parameter's relatively
easier to understand, right?
Because that's how much money
your deterministic investment
basically makes.
So [INAUDIBLE] is the
[INAUDIBLE] parameter.
So naively, you could
expect I need both mu-- let
me just remind you what mu is.
Mu and sigma, two
independent parameters.
But it turns out mu completely
drops out of the picture.
And this is because
of dynamic hedging,
because we hedged the position.
And so now this
equation-- since this
is basically Green's
function, and Green's function
tells us what's the
probability density
of the stock at some
time in the future,
if the stock were at
some point initially,
then basically this means
that we can simulate the stock
dynamics.
And we can price
derivatives, like,
using a very simple framework.
So what do we do?
We simply write the
equation for the stock
in the risk-neutral world.
Remember, the difference is
that instead of the actual drift
of the stock, mu, we substitute
here by the interest rate.
And this is basically how
much money, roughly speaking,
the bank account makes.
And what we do-- we start from
some stock value at time 0,
and then we simulate stock
along different paths.
So there are like
three paths here.
There could be like thousands.
So now-- and you
know, now, let's
say we know the stock
payoff at maturity.
And what you do-- then the price
of derivative is very simple.
Essentially, you take the
average of this payoff,
over the distribution.
And you know distribution,
because you just
simulated the stock price.
And you just discount it
with the interest rate.
So it's extremely simple.
So in principle,
implementing this--
I'd say if you have
package like MATLAB,
it probably takes like
maybe one hour at most,
implement let's say pricing
of Black-Scholes formula
via a Monte Carlo simulation.
So maybe if you have
time, you can try this
and see how your Monte
Carlo solution converges
to the exact result which was
first obtained by Black-Scholes
and Merton.
So basically, this is a
super powerful framework,
which basically tells
us something like this.
So it's not applicable
just to the stock prices,
but it's also applicable to
interest rate derivatives,
credit derivatives, and
foreign exchange derivatives,
so on and so forth.
Basically, the
idea is like this.
You have some-- the
payoff of your derivative
depends on various
financial variables.
And you simply simulate all of
them in the risk-neutral world.
Right?
So you simulate all
of them, and then you
could calculate the
average of the payoff.
And you just discount it.
And that's how you
can price derivatives.
So in principle, if you have
a flexible IT infrastructure,
like a financial institution,
so you can implement it.
And then you can price
pretty much everything.
That's basically how
exotic derivatives
are priced, whose prices
are not easy to obtain
using analytical methods.
Which is the case for a
large amount of derivatives.
So this is the
whole idea, right?
So Monte Carlo simulation is
a very fundamental concept.
So we do the simulation
in the risk-neutral world,
and there are certain rules
how to write these equations
for different asset classes--
could be stock again,
could be foreign exchange,
could be credit, could be rates,
whatever.
And then you do some kind of
sampling, you find average,
and then basically you are done.
So this is how it
works with the stock,
and let me just explain
how to generalize
all these ideas for the case
of interest rates and credit
derivatives.
So and-- let me just start from
the very basics of the interest
rate derivatives.
So of course the whole
point of these derivatives
is to allow financial
institutions or individuals
to manage their interest
rate risk better.
So businesses need money
to run their business.
So big institutions,
big corporations,
have billions, [INAUDIBLE]
hundreds of billions of dollars
of debt, and they know
how to risk manage
it, [INAUDIBLE] efficiently.
And just to make money, and
not even necessarily financial
institutions.
So of course if
you borrow money,
then you need to
pay some interest.
So you can think about
interest rate derivatives
as some kind of option on
the stochastic interest,
because let's say say today,
you can borrow money at 5%.
But tomorrow, this
rate can change.
So in order to control
this uncertainty,
you need to be able to
buy some derivatives,
just to hedge your
exposure, for example.
Or it might just speculate.
Maybe you just have some view
that rates will go up or down.
So it depends on the type
of investor or speculator,
whatever.
And so I mean this is
a very simple concept
of present value of money.
If I have dollar
today, it's definitely
better than the dollar
one year from now.
Let's say I have
a dollar, right?
But I will get it only
in one year from now.
So how much does it cost?
It's clear that if the
interest rate is 5%,
it roughly costs $0.95.
Right?
Because what do I do?
If the interest rate is
5%, then I take $0.95,
and I'd put it into bank
account, and I'd make 5%.
So I will get like $1
in one year from now.
So there exists very important
concept of the present value.
Or like time value of money.
Depending on where
in the future you
are, how much money
it costs today.
And people talk about-- it's
very often a fundamental notion
of the fixed income derivative,
is the discount factor.
So it essentially
tell you that OK,
if you have one dollar
today, it costs one dollar.
But if you have one
dollar in the future,
basically it costs
something else.
So this is a very important
notion in finance.
So I'll tell a little
bit more how [INAUDIBLE]
them together, this
functional [INAUDIBLE].
So another very important
thing in the interest rate
derivatives is the forward rate.
So remember, okay, so
we have discount factor.
And the very important
thing about discount factor
is it should start at 1.
Because a dollar
today is a dollar.
There is no uncertainty, right?
Thus it's clear
that this function
should be decaying, or at least
non-increasing, with time.
So that's why it's
very convenient
to parametrize this kind of
function with forward rates.
So this is some
positive forward rates.
And [INAUDIBLE] very convenient.
And remember, let's
say, in the example
below, like on this page,
if all maturities earn 5%,
then this is simply 5% a year.
So for this example, basically
your forward rate is just flat.
OK, so if this is an
example-- and when
you talk about interest
rate derivatives,
it's very convenient
to model the dynamics
of the forward rates.
So again, it's very
different from the stock,
because it's got an
additional dimension.
So if you model
the stock dynamics,
it's just a point process.
Right?
Let's say it's $100 today,
and then you start modeling.
Next, they'll go to $95, could
go to $105, so on and so forth.
But interest rates,
it's more about curve.
So it has an extra dimension--
it's a one-dimensional object.
And the reason is very simple.
In general, let's say if you
borrow money for one year,
then let's say you
pay one percent.
But if you borrow
for two years, it
might be that you borrow
it for 2%, and so on.
So there's a concept
of the yield curve.
And here basically tells us how
much different maturities make.
So in a typical situation,
with your curve,
if you don't have
some [INAUDIBLE]
of recession, which
sometimes happens,
it's usually upward sloping.
This basically means if you
borrow money for longer term,
you pay higher interest.
You can see it very easily.
Like for those who have
mortgages right there,
it's always like 15-year
mortgage rate is lower
than 30-year mortgage rate.
And just here I just
show-- to give you
a [INAUDIBLE], of where we are
right now in terms of interest
rates, basically I just show
you the yield of a 10-year US
Treasury note.
So what is 10-year
Treasury note?
Basically, the US
government borrows money
to finance its activities.
And then it works like this.
Let's say I'm an investor.
I'm giving the US
government $100.
And then every year, like
for the next 10 years--
more exactly, like
twice a year--
let's say they are
paying me some coupon.
Let's say if the interest
rate per year is 5%,
this means that if I give
the US government $100,
then the government pays
me $2.50 every half a year.
And at the very end,
in 10 years from now,
they must return
$100, the notional.
And basically, if you look again
how stochastic the rates are
right and what
kind of environment
we are in right now, you can
see that over the last about 50
years, we see very
interesting picture.
From about '60s
to about '80, '82,
we can see a tremendous
increase in interest rates.
And this is something which
looks very unbelievable right
now.
So this problem nowadays.
If one takes, let's
say a mortgage,
now a 30-year mortgage is
maybe 4%, 4.5% nowadays.
But let's say here,
about 30 years ago, it
was like a [INAUDIBLE] interest
rate-- very high inflation.
And mortgage rates
were in double digits.
It was not uncommon
to pay like 15%
if you would take
mortgage somewhere here.
So the rates were increasing.
But since then, we live in a
very different environment,
when interest rates
gradually go and go down.
So essentially, here,
basically it shows in 1980,
the US Government
would pay 12% a year
each year to borrow
money for 10 years.
So at the end of 2012, it
paid less than 2%-- just 1.7%.
So there like a very
clear trend, you know?
Something's going down.
So in recent years, there
is some kind of uptick here.
But you know, we always get
some kind of situation here.
So where are we going?
Nobody knows.
But really, we're in this
situation where interest rates
are extremely low.
It was nothing like
this, basically
for the last 50 years.
So it's very unusual, and you
have these very low interest
rates.
This means that the
economy is very weak,
because this means there's
not much demand on borrowing,
right?
Because corporations,
like individuals,
they don't want to borrow a lot,
because once [INAUDIBLE] again,
like supply-demand, right?
Because if you want to
borrow, basically you're
willing to pay higher rate.
So also, of course
another reason for this
is because-- we live in a
very unusual environment,
because the government
interferes a lot on the market.
So they're trying to make
the rates as low as possible,
just to make the interest
rates burden for corporations,
for private individuals
as small as possible.
And hopefully, we'll go
out of this recession.
But as I said, this
is very singular, very
unusual environment-- just to
understand what's going on.
And there a whole world
of interest rate-- yes?
AUDIENCE: But it pays to invest
in a non-productive access,
like real estate,
which are expected
to rise with time, without,
for example, [INAUDIBLE].
Doesn't it skew
whatever investment
is made toward assets which
are expected to rise with time?
It may not be
productive access--
DENIS GOROKHOV: Yes,
yes, but right now, I
mean I think even right
now, lots of people
are just scared to
buy real estate.
You never know what's
going on, right?
Because prices are
still pretty high, so
who knows what will happen?
So you're right.
There is some kind of
psychology [INAUDIBLE].
But many people who bought like
2006, whatever-- like before,
they basically
lost tons of money.
You never know.
So it's like when
you buy some assets,
you've got some finance.
Let's say fixed rate finance.
So you know how much
you're going to pay,
but where is the
guarantee that, you know--
I mean, long term, it
goes up, of course,
but long-term basically
means tens of years.
But if you look at the real
estate prices, for the last,
whatever, seven years.
We are going up right now, but
still, we didn't go through
for the minimum.
Like the [INAUDIBLE] maximum,
which you had before,
basically.
So you never know.
Yes, and so there's a whole
world of interest rate
derivatives.
So I'm just very briefly
explaining what it all means.
So usually-- here I mentioned
it's all about Treasury.
So it's all like
government-- it's
kind of yield implied
from the government bonds.
But usually, all the derivatives
are linked to another
very famous rate,
which is called LIBOR.
And LIBOR-- roughly
speaking, it's
a short-term rate at which
financial institutions
in London borrow money from each
other on an unsecured basis.
So there's a lot of caveats
here on this definition,
but that's roughly
what that means.
And there is like a fundamental
derivative in the interest rate
world is a LIBOR swap.
So the standard USD LIBOR
swap is something like this,
basically.
It's paying-- once
a three months,
it's paying three
months LIBOR rate.
And so this is
stochastic, right?
So basically, every day, there
is this certain procedure,
which tells us what this LIBOR,
this short-term borrowing rate
is.
And in exchange
for this, if you're
paying out this LIBOR
swap, this LIBOR rate,
you are receiving the fixed
rate, which is diminished.
So this is like fundamental
interest rate basically.
It's like, essentially, if you
believe that rates will go up
and you just want to
speculate, basically
you're trying to be long
LIBOR and short fixed rate,
and vice versa.
So this is a very important
instrument for pricing.
And it's all kinds
of derivatives
linked to this LIBOR rate.
For example, you can
talk about a swaption.
What is a swaption?
Swaption is a derivative
to enter an interest rate
swap in the future.
Remember like in the
equity option world,
let's say if I have a call
option on a stock, that's
the right to buy
a stock at a fixed
price-- it's fixed today-- like
at some time in the future.
Here, this is basically
the same idea.
If you're here today, at
sometime in the future
you can enter a swap,
a kind of contract,
which pays various
legs and there
is some price given for today.
And there are also all
kinds of false derivatives.
You can talk about rates.
Basically you can buy or sell
options on a particular LIBOR
rate.
Or there's also
cancel-able swaps,
which basically are
you can enter a swap,
but if you don't want to pay,
like, let's say, high rate
anymore, you can cancel it.
Of course, it's affecting
the price so on and so forth.
So, very important idea if
you think about all these
that it turns out that when you
price all these derivatives,
they all depend-- Their price
depends on these discount
factors.
And the discount factors
depend on these forward rates,
which is basically
trivial parametrization.
But it's very important,
very convenient, to work
with these forward rates.
And when we model interest rate
derivatives, using Monte Carlo
simulations, and there are no
analytical models available,
then [INAUDIBLE] model of
dynamics of forward rates.
And you can ask a question.
So how can we get, basically,
this curve in practice,
or this curve?
And it turns out that
the swap market tells us
how to obtain this curve.
So here I show some
quotes, real market quotes,
for interest rate swap
of different maturities.
Let's say two years,
three years, four years,
and so on and so forth.
And then if you add this
number and this number,
then you obtain the swap rate.
So if you take these
swap rates, then it
turns out that you can show
very easily that if you
know all these
numbers, then you will
be able to obtain this curve
in a pretty unique way.
So because of this
market of swaps--
so once again, if you add
these two numbers here,
then basically it tells
you that, for example,
for this instrument,
let's say, five years.
For the next five years,
I'm going to pay roughly
like 0.75% a year.
Right.
So these two
payments, basically,
correspond to like 0.75% in
exchange for the LIBOR payment,
right?
So if I enter a swap--
so I know that the I will
be paying fixed--
but I'll receive
floating, which is
random, because we
don't know what it is.
And [INAUDIBLE] is a
pretty complicated concept.
The idea is very simple.
So basically the
swap market allows
you to obtain this
discount factor-- basically
this function-- which tells
you how much your dollar
in the future is today.
So if you know how
much a dollar is,
then you know how much C
dollars, basically, cost.
Then basically, let's
say you have C dollars.
Then you simply multiply
them by the discount factor,
and that's what the present
value of your fixed rate
payment is.
So remember that
finance [INAUDIBLE]
very important things.
In finance, at least in
the derivative world,
we typically-- what is called
PV or present value of all
our future payments, right?
So we have some future
liability, which
is something very complicated.
I say, I'll pay you
something very complicated,
pay off in 10 years from now.
But we are trying to understand
how much it's worth today.
Because idea for this business
is clients come to the bank.
And they say, I want
this derivative.
You sell this derivative.
You charge the money
right now, and you
spend this money on hedging.
Of course, you try to charge
them a little bit more
because you need to
still make living.
But in [INAUDIBLE] basically
is like you've spent
most of your money on hedging.
But you to try to come
up with a number today.
Here's, again, a
very simple example.
So if you know, once again,
how much your dollar is
in the future, then
you can present
value, PV, every payment.
So let's say in 10 years
from now, d is equal to 0.5,
then if you payoff's $1,000, the
present value is equal to $500.
Because, again, the argument
is very simple, right?
You take $500 today and
invest for 10 years,
and you get $1,000
in the future.
This is the
replication argument.
Another very
important thing here,
is that if you have
an interest rate
swap, which is paying LIBOR.
And let's say on a notional.
Let's say I pay you LIBOR,
which is some rate which
is measured in percent.
LIBOR is like a 1%
a year, for example.
Then notional of the
swap is $1 million
which means that the floating
rate payment is based on $1
million times 1% is $10,000.
So it turns out that
very interesting thing
is that if you pay
LIBOR rate and if you
pay the notional
at the very end,
then the present value of
this is equal to the notional.
So it's the beauty of
floating rate is security.
[INAUDIBLE] is basically that
if you pay the current market
rate all the time, then
the price of your security
is always equal to the notional.
It's very nice fact which
is also fundamental here.
And very interesting
thing would happen
after crisis is that all
the derivatives have become
what's called collateralized.
So you need to post
some money all the time.
So there's another concept
of OIS discounting,
which I don't talk about here.
The main idea which you
need to understand here
is that we have this function,
like discount function, which
shows us again how much the
dollar is worth in the future.
And using this function, we
can price all kinds of swaps.
So we can PV the value of
the swap today using this.
So the idea of interest
rate derivatives
it's all about dynamics
of the yield curve.
It's basically how
your discount function
or how your yields,
future yields, evolve.
The whole idea is
similar to the stock.
So again, at time 0 you
start from some curve.
For example, something
like this, right?
From some curve
which is shown here.
And then it stopped
evolving and you
want to be able to model
it mathematically and price
all kinds of derivatives.
So there is like a very
interesting difference
between stock options
and interest rate options
because for the stock options,
we know the price today.
If it's a liquid
stock, it's just known.
We know what it's
trading right now.
But for the yield
curve, it's different.
We first need to take
the swap markets quotes
and do what is
called bootstrapping
to get the function d of t.
The next step, we
need to specify
the volatility of different
forward rates in the future
and we need to come up
with some kind of dynamics
which describes the future
dynamics of forward rates.
And then once we
have this, we can
use the Monte Carlo framework to
price all kinds of derivatives.
So before I start talking
about the HJM framework here,
I just want to
mention that there
are some other more simple
models which are historically
appear before the HJM model
which basically describe
the dynamics of the short rate.
And so the most famous
ones are the Ho-Lee model,
Hull-White model, and
so-called CIR model.
And basically, the
idea is that if you
have this function for forward
rates-- which I wrote here.
So they describe dynamics,
instantaneous dynamics,
of this rate.
So instead of modeling
the whole curve,
you model only just this
short rate and so on.
So some of these models
are particular case
of the HJM model.
Some of them are not.
But just to mention.
And basically the idea, then, of
the interest rate derivatives,
for example, let's say I want
to price an option that in five
years from now, I enter a
particular interest rate
swap which pays 5% on the
fixed leg and receives LIBOR.
So I need to model the
dynamic of future yields.
And remember, it's a very
important thing that, again,
because we have
the curve, now we
have two different times here.
For the stock derivatives, we
just basically write dynamics,
d of S_t is equal to something.
And t is just basically
instantaneous time.
Here t stands for
And T, capital T, stands
for the future time.
Here.
So essentially if
you're here, you're
looking at the forward
rate somewhere here.
And then you basically
describe with dynamics.
I don't want to go into
details, but again,
using this very fundamental
result in pricing theory
like Ito's Lemma, you can derive
the equation for this drift.
So the problem is it
turns out it's always
the case in the Monte
Carlo simulation.
So you [INAUDIBLE] some time
equation and you have drift
and you have volatility.
So it turns out that
this drift, the real time
drift, because you hedge,
drops out of your equation.
And it turns out that
for the interest rate,
there is some complication.
In the risk-neutral world, this
real-world drift [INAUDIBLE]
by some equation which
depends on sigma.
So if you do the
calculation, then you
will see that in the
risk-neutral world,
if you [INAUDIBLE]
of following form,
which is some
non-local equation.
But it is what it is.
So it's very straightforward.
I encourage you just to, if you
have time, to go through this
and really understand
how it works.
But now once we have this,
the model for interest rate
derivatives is very simple.
And remember that
in the stock world--
let me go back just
to this equation.
So we started from some
stochastic differential
equation.
And then we simulate
different paths.
And then basically we
average over the pay-off
here at maturity
of the derivative,
when actually we do the payment.
And here the situation
is very similar.
So we have some
initial curve which we
obtain from the market today.
And this curve dynamics is
described by this equation.
Then we have distribution
of this curve in the future,
and then you can price
all kinds of derivatives.
So again, it's a very
fundamental framework.
So very general.
So once the curve and
the volatility are known,
you simply run this simulation
and you get your pay-off.
So basically that's
how it works.
And now another example,
which is basically--
of this HJM model, is
basically credit derivatives.
So I don't have
much time, but just
mention-- I'll go very
briefly what's going on.
So if you give money
just to someone,
like to the
corporations, then there
is a probability that you
won't get your money back.
So corporations issue
bonds, financial instruments
to raise capital.
It's, again, very similar
to the US treasuries.
And so you give them $100 and
they pay you 5% < every year.
And then let's say in 10
years, if it's a 10 year bond,
they are supposed to
give your money back.
But this might not happen.
Corporations default because
they make their own decisions.
Like something went
wrong with economy,
and so on and so forth.
It happens.
So there is some risk
which is indicated here.
We just call it default risk.
So corporations or
private individuals,
they have a right to
default. So they can default.
And this is reflected in
the coupons which they pay.
So for the US government
at the end of 2012.
A 10 year bond would
pay just 1.7% a year.
Again, we are in extremely
low environment which
looks like almost nothing.
And remember that even if
you're an investor and if you
buy this bond, then you
get your 1% interest
but then you need to
pay taxes on the profit.
So the return is
really very small.
So then, of course, if
you're an investor, then OK.
The US government securities
are assumed to be risk-free,
so you won't be
able to lose money.
So this is a very
important benchmark.
But then you can buy
bonds of corporations.
But, of course, to compensate
for possible default,
they pay higher coupon.
For example, at the end of
2012, Morgan Stanley bonds
would pay around,
let's say 5% a year.
Significantly higher.
Some governments
are right now very
close to default.
So some time ago,
for example, when Morgan Stanley
bonds would pay 5% a year.
But say, Greece bonds
would pay 25%, 30% a year.
Because nobody knows what's
going to happen there.
It's clear that the economy
is not in good shape
and it all depends
on the bailouts.
Or these bailouts are
conditioned, for example,
that the right
government-- if you'll
be in power and the
[INAUDIBLE] is unclear.
So there's lots of uncertainty.
Such uncertainties, that's
why, essentially, the yield--
investors tell you would
require very high yield.
And in the credit derivatives,
the fundamental instrument,
is credit default swap.
So if you have a risky
bond, then in order
to protect from default you
can go, let's say to a bank,
and buy a credit default swap.
It basically means
that if you hold
a bond and default happens, then
the seller of this protection
will compensate
you for the loss.
For example, let's say
you bought a bond at $100.
And then, let's say, in one
year the corporation defaults.
And then what happens
in this event?
Then court.
Court happens.
And the judge decides how
much money is recovered.
And this money is distributed
to the bond investors.
They're first in the queue.
And then if, let's say, $0.70
on the dollar were recovered,
then the default swap will
pay you $32 which you lost.
And very fundamental concept in
the world of credit derivatives
is market implied
survival probability.
So in principle,
credit default swaps
are available for
different entities.
Let's say like Morgan Stanley.
It could be Verizon.
Could be AT&T and
so on and so forth.
And [INAUDIBLE] require
different payments.
For example, let's
say if credit default
swap for Morgan
Stanley, probably
is like 5 year maturity, you
pay around 100 basis points.
And if there is
some-- like Greece,
probably, you pay like 500,
maybe 1,000 basis points
or something like this.
So market differentiates.
And based on this, you can then
do a very simple calculation.
And you consider, it's very
easy to come with a concept
of the survival probability.
Roughly speaking if, let's
say, default protection
on some reference entity
is worth 1% a year.
And then what do we see?
Then with probability 99% a
year, you will get your money.
If probability 1% per
year, you will get nothing.
So you can think
about it like this.
This means you can say
the probability to default
is roughly 1% a
year, in this case.
And then we could talk about
survival probabilities,
which is basically
one [INAUDIBLE]
default probability.
And you can then come
up with the concept
of survival probabilities,
which you can again
parametrize with forward rates
which are called hazard rates.
So credit derivatives,
in a sense,
they're similar to
interest rate derivatives.
Remember, in the case of
interest rate derivatives,
we were talking about
discount factors.
So this is like
the present value.
Present value of money.
In terms of world of credit
derivatives-- besides this,
because of course
interest rates are also
very important for
credit derivatives--
we talk about
survival probability.
Today it's equal to
1, but then it decays.
And let's say if you
have a US government,
basically it always stay at one.
And let's say if it's
like Morgan Stanley,
it goes like this.
If it's some distressed
European sovereign,
it will go like this.
So basically it's
market-implied probability
of default based on the
credit default swap market.
And the idea of the HJM model
for the credit derivatives
is that-- similar to the dynamic
of forward rates in interest
rate case-- you simply describe
the dynamics of hazard rates
which parametrize your
survival probabilities.
And now let me see.
Let me show an example of very
important type of derivatives,
which are priced
using credit models.
Let's talk about the
corporate callable bonds.
So it's a very
simple instrument.
Again, I'm a corporation.
I borrow $100 from you.
And let's say I'm paying
you 5% every year.
But I have the
right at any time--
or, let's say, once in three
months-- return you this $100,
and basically close the deal.
So why is that so valuable
for the corporations?
Because today's
environment is such
that I borrow at
a very high rate.
In this example, let's
say I am paying 5% a year.
And I issued a 10 year bond and
there's $100 million notional.
So basically this means
that every year, I
am paying to the investor 5%.
$5 million.
But let's say I'm paying 5%.
I need this money to run
my business and so on.
So it's some burden, but
usually all the corporations
have significant amount of debt.
So it's good to have debt if
you know how to manage it.
Now let's say in three years
from now, situation changed.
So now I can borrow
money for seven years,
because initially I issued
the bond for 10 years.
And now I have seven
years remaining,
but it turns out I
can issue just a 3%.
Basically this
means if I do this,
if I exercise my call option,
then I will save 5 minus 3--
2%-- times $100 million
times seven years.
So it's $14 million.
So that's kind of why callable
debt, it's good to issue it,
because you can save money.
It's very similar to what's
happening right now also
for private individuals.
Because in recent year
or couple of years,
there was lot of refinancing
activity in the US.
Remember rates are at
historical low right now.
So rates are going
down, down, down.
So let's say if you took
out a mortgage here at 6%,
it was like you could
refinance at here, for example,
the same mortgage.
You could [INAUDIBLE]
like at 3.5%.
So the same [INAUDIBLE] has
happened to corporations.
So in the US, by default,
all mortgages are callable.
And basically by
default, everybody
has a right to refinance.
So it's not like you
issue a 30 year bond
and then even you're
paying a huge coupon,
even you can refinance
lower percent-- which
might be the case for
corporation, by the way.
But by law in the US, all the
mortgages can be refinanced.
So basically, that's the idea.
So if you price this kind of
instrument as callable bond
then you need to
take into account,
of course, the interest
rate risk because you need
to understand what is the
current level of interest rate
you can charge.
And also you need
to take into account
the quality of the issuer.
So if, let's say again, Greece.
Or, let's say, Morgan
Stanley issue debt right now,
then Morgan Stanley would
pay significantly less.
It's all [INAUDIBLE]
on the fair market.
[INAUDIBLE] result
and subsidies.
And, of course, Morgan Stanley
would pay significantly less
in the interest because
for the case of Greece,
it is a much higher
default risk.
And as I mentioned,
the idea is that you,
in the world of
credit derivatives,
there is the concept
of hazard rates
which, again, some curve which
shows how risky the issuer is
at some point in the future.
And here I show the dynamics
for the forward rates,
and here is the dynamics
of hazard rates.
It shows you, basically,
how risky the issuer is.
And then using similar
approach-- I show, give you
as an exercise-- you
can prove again--
it turns out if you know the
volatility of hazard rates,
then you know how to simulate
the dynamics of hazard rates.
So essentially, it's the
dynamics of all this.
So again, it's the idea-- let
me go back just to the stock
case-- again, it's the
idea, it's very simple.
So you have all the
dynamic variables
like rates and
[INAUDIBLE], in this case.
Then what you do, you simulate
that in risk-neutral world.
You have different path.
And then you simply
average over the pay-off.
So this is the beauty of
the risk-neutral pricing.
There is a visual framework
which is basically implemented
at all the major banks.
Which is really like
the right approach
to price very exotic
derivatives for which
it's very hard to find the
exact analytical formulas.
And let me show you one
example of securities
which are issued by big banks.
And that's where this HJM model
and Monte Carlo simulation
are used all the time
because the pay-offs are
very complicated.
And example of such a product
is called structured note.
So what's a structured note?
It's-- again, corporations need
to raise money just to run this
business.
But, of course, I cannot
just get this money for free.
I need to pay some interest.
And again, if you look at
what happened last year.
Again, at the end of last year,
for example a US 20 year bond
would pay 1.7%.
And if you also
pay all the taxes,
then you probably get
something like 1.1%.
And this might be even
lower than inflation.
So investors, especially
long-term investors,
they are not interested in
investing in the US treasuries
because although it's risk
free, but there's no return.
So you want to
generate some money.
So what can you do, then?
OK, so you don't want to
invest into treasuries.
So then you can try to
find some corporate bonds.
Again, corporates are risky
compared to the United States
government.
So typical coupon paid
by the corporate bonds
would be higher.
So let's say 5% for a
non-distressed typical US
corporation.
But again, 5%.
Then you need to pay, let's
say, 30% tax top of this.
So you're left 3.3%.
There's inflation and
so on and so forth.
So it still looks
like a low return.
Of course,
[INAUDIBLE] below, you
can buy some distressed bonds,
say from Greece or maybe
from some distressed
corporations, which
is a much higher.
But it becomes
more like gambling.
There's so much
uncertainties there,
so it's more like you
can get very high return,
but you can lose everything
because basically you're
bearing very high credit risk.
So what to do in this situation?
Turns out that banks issue
very special securities called
structured notes which are very
attractive to some investors.
So let's say Morgan
Stanley-- but instead
of issuing vanilla bond,
I am issuing-- and at 5%,
let's say for 10 years-- I issue
a bond which pays 10% a year.
So much higher coupon.
But I pay you 10% only if
certain market conditions
are satisfied.
So let's say market
condition like this.
30 year swap rate is higher
than two year swap rate.
Let's go back to the
picture which I drew.
So essentially this means
that if you borrow money, then
the short term borrowing
rate is smaller
than the long term
borrowing rate, which
usually is the case.
So basically, let's assume
I pay you 10% percent
if two conditions are satisfied.
1% is the 30 year borrowing
rate in the economy right
now is higher than
two year borrowing
rate, which is this condition.
Plus this second condition.
S&P 500 index is
higher than 880.
So now if these
conditions are satisfied,
then the investor will get 10%.
If one of these
conditions breaks down,
the investor would get nothing.
So there are many
investors who would
like to bear this kind
of risk because they
have certain view on how
the economy would develop.
Because right now, for
example, S&P 500 index
is pretty close to 2,000.
So it's very unlikely
that it'll go down
by the factor of
two, which is 880.
So it's very low probability.
And then also investor believes
that this will never happen.
So we always will
be in the economy
where it's still more
expensive to borrow long-term
than short term.
So in this case, it
turns out that the coupon
can be enhanced.
This is a whole idea
of the structured note.
So instead of setting
like a plain coupon, 5%,
I am selling [INAUDIBLE]
the derivative.
And if investors like
it, it's kind of gambling
but in educated
way because there's
certain economic meaning
of these conditions.
But this can get high return.
And this is a very popular way
of financing because it turns
out that investors are buying
this kind of instruments,
but they are very unique.
There's a lot very liquid.
Therefore when issue
this kind of instrument,
even if you price it correctly
using all the models,
the bank or
financial institution
which issues these instruments
can make some extra money.
So effectively it's cheaper
to issue these instruments
than to issue vanilla bonds.
And all of these big banks,
they have all the machinery
to risk manage this kind
of [INAUDIBLE] derivatives.
So they know what
they are doing.
So they sell this
kind of product,
and they're hedging
their exposure.
And they realize some
profit because you
can't identify how much
[INAUDIBLE] instrument is.
So it's good for banks.
And it's also good for
investors because they
are looking for this kind
of yield enhancement.
They want to have
a higher yield.
And they are
taking-- and they're
willing to take this risk.
But again, it's an
educated risk because like,
this condition, for
example, here, they
have a very clear
economical meaning.
So if an investor
understands what's going on,
then it's a reasonable risk.
And, of course, what
do you do in this case
if you want to model
something like this?
Then it's very
complicated to find
any kind of analytic
approximations
here in the real world.
So what do we do?
We simulate the
stock market price.
We simulate the 30 year
yield and 10 year yield.
And we simulate Morgan
Stanley's credit spread.
And we do it all simultaneously,
at the same time.
And then we see in the
Monte Carlo simulation
if this condition is satisfied
for every coupon date,
then we're paying 10%.
If something is broken,
then we are paying 0.
So if we simulate many,
many paths like this
and then we calculate
the average value of it.
And then we come
up with the price
and then we quote this
price to the investor.
And again, I say, these
products are very nonstandard.
That's fine.
You can make some extra money.
And as a firm, you
save money because it's
cheaper than to issue
plain vanilla bonds.
And just to give
you the idea where
we are in terms of numbers.
So here there is a
graph of difference
between 30 year borrowing
rate and two year borrowing
rate for the last decade.
So you see, this
difference always positive.
It was negative only very
shortly for some time
around 2005, 2006.
So it's very interesting thing.
So when you price
derivative, then there's
a notion of
market-implied numbers.
It turns out if you look at
how different instruments are
priced on the market,
then the probability--
Then you can ask
a question: What
is the probability
that this-- Let's
say if I run, for example, this
stochastically for the last 10
years, then how--
what the probability
that this difference
is positive.
And then it turns out
probability is only
80% percent.
Whereas in reality, it was
realized only for a few days.
So it's significantly lower.
So basically, then, the
investor says like this.
So market give me the
discount, like 80%.
But I know that this almost
never happen in the past.
Therefore I believe that it
will not happen in the future.
Maybe it will happen,
but I will still
make some extra money
because of this.
So basically we have [INAUDIBLE]
enhancement by a factor 1
divided by 0.8.
1.25%.
Second thing is about S&P 500.
If you look at the history of
this index, which is basically
the main US market
index, then you
see that it was historically
above 880 level for 94 days out
of 100 days.
So very, very high probability.
But the market implies this will
be the case only in 75% case.
The credit investor
would say like this.
OK, now S&P 500 is around 1,800.
So what the probability it's
going to drop below 880?
Of course there is
some probability,
but if it's going to
happen because it will mean
a very serious
recession, and it looks
like the economy is improving.
The market might
drop down, but maybe
to the level of 1,500, 1,400.
But not that low.
Therefore the investor believes
that he, by taking this risk,
he will again get
a higher coupon.
So [INAUDIBLE] very popular
instruments which are
solely price by Monte Carlo
simulation, which-- we have
big businesses, for example,
like Morgan Stanley, whose
goal is to raise capital
by selling these exotic
products and hedging them using
the Monte Carlo framework.
And if the interest rates
are crucial for dynamics,
then we use the HJM model for
simulating interest rates.
So that's everything
I wanted to tell you
about today, so
thank you very much.
[APPLAUSE]
DENIS GOROKHOV: Yeah?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
simulation.
Is there some choice-- you
might make certain choices
based on historical precedence?
DENIS GOROKHOV: It's
a very good question.
So, in reality.
So here's what happens.
So let's go to a very
simple case of stock prices.
So again, r here basically
is just the borrowing rate.
It's like, let's say, whatever
the bank account gives.
Which is known.
So the only parameter which
isn't known is volatility.
So usually, you have
liquid stocks, for example.
Like IBM, Apple.
Then there are a lot
of derivatives traded,
which are very liquid.
This means that you can imply
this sigma from the price
of liquid derivatives.
Because you know, for example,
that this particular option--
let's say today
Apple traded at 600--
and you know that at the money
option, so option with a strike
600, in one year now, for
example, it's worth whatever.
Like $50, for example.
By knowing this, you
can imply this sigma.
So the whole idea is like this.
So you take very liquid
derivatives, like standard call
options, and you
imply this sigma.
And then you use
this model to price
really truly exotic derivatives,
which are not vitally
available.
That's how big banks make money.
Because we know
how to price them.
We have clients come in.
And we see the prices of
very liquid instruments
and we buy them to hedge.
So very often what we do is
that we do some very complicated
deal, but we have an
ability to off-load it
into simpler contracts,
which we know how to price.
That's the idea.
And the same is true for
all the other derivatives,
from credit derivatives or
[INAUDIBLE] derivatives.
So you try to imply the
sigma from the market.
If there is no way
to do this-- which
is very often the case for
credit derivatives because
for the credit
derivatives, credit vol--
is not very liquid,
not liquidly traded.
Then the best thing
that you can do
is to take historical estimates.
So we also do this.
There is nothing else.
Yeah.
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: On your
last slide where
you talked about the implied
frequency of the S&P 500
being lower than 880?
DENIS GOROKHOV: Yeah.
AUDIENCE: Was that
from historical quotes
or current quotes?
DENIS GOROKHOV:
OK This number, I
think, if you go to the end
of 2012 and go back to 2002.
10 years into the past.
Then I think it was
above 880 in 94% of case.
We can go back.
So remember, just to the slide
I showed in the very beginning.
Here it was, right.
So 880 is somewhere here.
2012 is here.
You go back 2002.
It was below 880 around
2000, internet bubble.
And around, say, 2008, 2009 when
we had major banking crisis.
[INAUDIBLE] just now.
So you can see
probability is not
very high based on historicals.
These kind of people
believe that in the future
it might happen,
but then the stock
will go back again because
the government will intervene
and so on and so forth.
That's the way of thinking
of these investors
who invest into structured
notes like this.
AUDIENCE: So for the
implied frequency,
that's from the current--
DENIS GOROKHOV: Exactly.
AUDIENCE: --option prices--
Exactly.
So now that's how
historical was obtained.
Ah, let me see.
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah.
Well, let me see.
So, yes.
So it's like this.
So you're today and you
have your Monte Carlo model.
And you simulated going
forward for 10 years
and you see what the
probability to be below 880.
And actually, much
higher because usually
the market is
extremely risk-averse.
So if you're buying a deep
out of the money option
you usually-- there is--
everybody requires premium.
Because if this happens,
if you don't really like
charge enough money, basically
that you're out of business.
That is how I obtain
this number, what, 75%.
Whatever.
OK.
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: So is the pricing
of these more exotic products
totally reliant
upon Monte Carlo,
or are there other techniques?
DENIS GOROKHOV: I mean,
usually it's Monte Carlo.
So there are some derivatives
where analytical approximations
are available.
For example, for
interest rate derivative.
Swaps are like a very
simple linear product.
To price them, you
need discount function.
So it's just arithmetic.
Of course, it's all done,
just simple arithmetic.
For swaptions,
standard swaptions,
there is a model
called SABR model which
allows some kind of
semi-analytical solutions,
which are approximate
but of high quality.
Then you can do it.
But there are different
schools of thought.
Because with some
approximations,
which might fail for some
if maturity is very long,
or it's very-- very deep
out of the money option.
So very often what traders do,
even if their official numbers
are only-- more simplified
models which kind of has
some formula, they still round
the Monte Carlo simulation
for the whole
portfolio to understand
what the most complicated
model, like in terms
of your present value
of your portfolio,
in terms of the risk.
But, of course,
this kind of double
range accruals, which
are just [INAUDIBLE].
It's impossible to build any
meaningful analytical model.
You can do something,
but you won't
be able to be competitive.
It's just all Monte
Carlo simulation.
AUDIENCE: So you said
usually this whole simulation
process takes an hour
on a MATLAB program?
DENIS GOROKHOV: No.
No.
It takes probably
like one hour just
to write the whole program,
because it's very simple.
So what you do, you
have Brownian motion.
But what you do.
MATLAB generates
Brownian motion.
So you just do it.
And then you write the
change in your price
is equal to your
drift, which you know,
plus some random number.
And you basically just
simulate different path.
And then if you
price a call option,
you know the distribution
of your stock prices,
let's say, in one year
from now with maturities.
And you just do average.
So it might take
someone 15 minutes
to write this kind of program.
This is so you can verify
numerically the accuracy
of the-- verify numerically
Black-Scholes formula,
for example.
But the idea fits
very simple here.
But, of course, for
these complicated models,
which you-- for term
structure process like HJM,
because it's already
one-dimensional object.
And, of course, it's
much more complicated
because besides
pricing, you need
to have this idea of
calibration as you mentioned,
because these volatilities are
not just usually historical.
They're implied from
other instruments.
So what you do in
practice, like this.
So if you have liquid
instruments, liquid options,
you have the model.
But the model has
unknown parameters.
First, we do the calibration.
So we make sure that
our model prices all
the simple instruments.
And then we take the
derivative whose price
is unknown because it's just
something very complicated.
And then we just price
it, but our model's
calibrated to
simple derivatives.
And this tells us--
then this model,
after pricing it and
running sensitivity
with respect to
market parameters,
tells us how to hedge it.
That's the idea.
AUDIENCE: You ought to
do post-hoc analyses
to see how the models did in
the past so you can adjust them.
DENIS GOROKHOV: Yeah.
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: Is that a big
part of what you have to do?
DENIS GOROKHOV: I
will say in general we
are moving to this direction.
In general, of course, for Monte
Carlo-- from the [INAUDIBLE]
point of view for complicated
Monte Carlo model,
it's very difficult
to do technically.
It's very difficult.
But if you do it,
you cannot afford simple models
like for swaps and so on.
AUDIENCE: --historical
experience
with the projection
that you made.
DENIS GOROKHOV: No.
But the situation,
it's very different.
So we don't make any
predictions here, remember.
It's risk-neutral pricing.
Just no prediction here.
What we do here is like this.
If we are a bank
and we want to trade
all kinds of very
exotic derivatives
which nobody knows
how to price but
we have clients who want to buy
them with different reasons.
Might want to
speculate or they want
to manage their risk exposure
and so on and so forth.
So nobody knows except
for like 10, 20 banks,
how to price them.
Because this is like, you
need to have infrastructure.
You need to know how to do this.
Then you need to have
some business channels,
how to off-load this risk.
So this is some very
exotic products.
So now the idea of dynamic
hedging is like this.
Remember, in the case
of Black-Scholes.
You buy an option
and then you hedge it
by holding a certain
amount of the underlying.
So you don't make any money.
But you want to make sure that
whatever happens to the market,
you're fully hedged.
So the market moves here,
you don't make any money.
The market moves down,
So the way how you make money
in this situation, basically
this Black-Scholes formula,
in this case, the price which
you charge for the
option is the price
of executing the
hedging strategy.
So if you charge
a little bit more,
this is extra money
which you can make.
So it's very different.
So what you just mentioned
is like proprietary business.
Big banks, they are not
supposed to do this.
It's more like a
hedge fund world.
Very different models.
What we do, we try to manage
big portfolios of derivatives,
all kinds of derivatives.
And we try to price them and
charge a little bit extra so
that we can make our living.
But on the other hand,
we don't take any risk.
That's the idea.
[INAUDIBLE] just models.
So from point of view in
terms of testing historically,
you can still ask a question.
Let's say if I go back 10 years.
And let's say 10 years
ago, I would sell,
for example, this stock option.
And for the next 10 years,
using historical data,
I see basically
how-- my model then
tells me what my Greeks or
like what my sensitivity
with respect to the
underlying-- what
my sensitivity with
respect to underlying is.
And then you can ask a question.
How was this delta H
performing historically?
Which is a reasonable
question because maybe you
assume that the model
pretty much continuous.
But maybe if your
dynamics is very jerky,
then you can just lose money
because you just don't take
into account these effects.
This is an example of historical
analysis which we may run,
but it has nothing to
do with prediction here.
So it's a whole different world.
So it's risk-neutral pricing.
So we don't take any risk.
That's the whole idea.
But due to the fact that
derivatives are very complex,
even in this case, still
banks bear some residual risk,
because remember we cannot
exactly off-load it, the risk.
So we still have
some assumptions
that we can re-balance our
position dynamically and move
forward, basically,
and not lose money.
That's the idea of it.
AUDIENCE: I have a question
about the Monte Carlo pricing.
You can set up the Monte
Carlo using implied parameters
from current prices
of various derivatives
in the market, which gives
you a good baseline price.
I'm wondering what
other Monte Carlos
do you do to have a robust
estimate of pricing, hedging
cost.
I would think that there
would be, I don't know,
maybe some stress scenarios
in the market or alternatives.
You probably don't
just do one Monte Carlo
study with current parameters.
You probably have
different sets.
And I'm wondering how
extensive is that?
DENIS GOROKHOV: Absolutely.
You are right.
So if you just do
the Monte Carlo,
then you just know the price.
But price is nothing,
because dynamic hedging,
all this business
of derivatives,
it's not just about how
much it's right now,
but what to do if the
market behaves this way.
So of course you could
collate all your Greeks.
That's very important.
But Greeks is like,
say, your delta.
It's all about linear terms.
So of course it's a
very important thing.
What happen to the
portfolio, let's
say, if there is a very
sharp, for example,
jump in interest rate.
So let's say, what happens
if rates jump forward by 1%.
Or if they jump down.
What happens if volatility
in a particular time,
region, for example, blows up.
You run all these
kind of analyses.
So it's big departments
at the banks who
look at all this kind of risks.
So it all comes to
one business unit
which looks all kinds
of risks of the firm.
It's a very big
thing for the bank.
This notion of stress test.
Basically right now,
all of the banks
are very heavily regulated
by the government.
So the government can
tell us what happens.
For example, for
the whole bank--
not just for a particular
desk which trades,
whatever, swaptions.
What happens to all your bank,
to all kinds of cash flows
which you can have
if, let's say,
interest rates jump
by 100% percent.
We have a huge group of people,
quants, IT, risk managers,
who are looking at all
these numbers trying
to understand it.
And for a big bank, very
non-trivial problem, actually.
So it's very good point.
But, of course, we
do as good as we can.
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: Well, thanks again.
And for a little
time afterwards for--
[APPLAUSE]
DENIS GOROKHOV: Thank you.